

SENIOR ENGINEER · RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE MANAGER · MACROECOLOGIST

☑ erik.kusch@nhm.uio.no | R<sup>6</sup> Erik Kusch | ② 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🎢 www.erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 🥩 KuschErik

## Research Profile

I am a macroecologist and data scientist specialised in streamlining work-flows as well as integrating and analysing big data. I use and develop quantitative tools to study ecosystem resilience and landscape-scale biodiversity to understand ecosystems trajectories through time and space. My current work includes coordination efforts of European biodiversity data research infrastructures inference, software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation as well as analysis and simulation of ecological networks.

## Education

#### PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

01/2020 - 04/2023

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

**Dissertation:** A Macroecological Perspective to Ecological Networks - Exploring the Impacts of Climate-Driven Biodiversity

Change & Contrasting and Benchmarking Network Inference Approaches

#### M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UiB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

**B.Sc. in Biology** 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

## **Specialised Training**

## Open, Reproducible, and Transparent Science in Ecology

Finse, Norway

University of Bergen 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats 26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

**An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics** 

Glasgow, Scotland 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

University of Glasgow

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc

Helsinki. Finland

University of Helsinki 02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020

**Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems** 

Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg 23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

# **Experience**

## Senior Engineer / Research Infrastructure Manager

Oslo Norway

NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO

03/2023 - PRESENT

Research Fellow

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

Bergen, Norway 09/2019 - 12/2019

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROOF, UNIVERSITY OF DER

Saxony, Germany

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP

mony, cennary

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS

04/2016 - 06/2016

#### **Research and Teaching Assistant**

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO

05/2017 - 07/2017

07/2018

1

## **Student Assistant**

BOTANICAL INSTITUTE, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)

05/2016 - 08/2016; 02/2015 - 08/2015

Zoological Collection, Technical University Dresden (TUD)

04/2016 - 05/2016; 11/2013 - 08/2015

Teaching & Supervision Activity	
Bayesian Networks Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
AU Bayes Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
Excursions into Biostatistics	🔾 Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	😵 Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
Biological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP)	😵 Course Web Page
Author	Aarhus University
Teaching Assistant	Aarhus University
Applied Statistics	22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021
STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING	03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020
GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020
Instructor & Advisor	
Ecoinformatics & Biodiversity Masters Seminars (EBMS), Aarhus University	03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021
CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN	08/2017 - 07/2018
Talks & Workshops	
Accessing and Referencing GBIF Data for Research	Trondheim, Norway
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, LIVING NORWAY COLLOQUIUM 2023	24/05/2023
Climate Data with the KrigR Pipeline Workshop	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, 5TH CONFERENCE OF NORDIC SOCIETY OIKOS 2022	07/07/2022
Ecological Network Inference - Pipedream or Pipeline	Oxford, England
Invited Speaker, SalGo Team, University of Oxford	22/05/2022
KrigR - The R Package	Hamburg, Germany
Speaker, AK Klima Interimstreffen	25/03/2021
KrigR - Downscaling State-of-the-Art Climate Data for Macroecologists	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, BIOCHANGE METHODS WORKSHOPS	12/11/2020
KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study	
Invited Speaker, Salgo Team, University of Oxford	18/06/2020
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing	
Invited speaker, Ecosystem Research Group, University of Oxford	15/10/2019
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019	04/10/2019

Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing

Invited Speaker, Ecosystem Research Group, University of Oxford

Speaker, International Society for Ecological Modelling Conference 2019

Invited Speaker, Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity Research Group, University of Aarhus

Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance

Bergen, Norway

Invited Speaker, BIO Day, University of Bergen

Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data

Invited Speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow

Social Data

Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance

15/03/2019

Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data

Invited Speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow

109/01/2019

## **Extracurricular Activity**

### **Group Member**

Statistics Journal Club, University of Glasgow	03/2021 - 03/2023
Spatial Shared-Interest Group, University of Glasgow	03/2021 - 03/2023
Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen	09/2018 - 12/2019
EECRG Reading Group, University of Bergen	10/2017 - 12/2019

#### **Leader & Dungeon Master**

University of Oslo Natural History Museum Dungeons & Dragons Group Aarhus University Section 05/2023 - PRESENT FOR Ecoinformatics Dungeons & Dragons Group 03/2022 - 01/2023

#### **Elected Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD**

Technical University of Dresden 10/2013 - 10/2015

Dresden, Germany

- -

# Writing

## NetworkExtinction - R Package to Simulate Extinction Propagation & Rewiring Potential in Ecological Networks

M.Isidora Ávila-Thieme\*, **Erik Kusch**\*, Derek Corcoran\*, ..., Navarrete, Pablo A. Marquet (\* ... joint first-authorship)

Methods in Ecology and Evolution - 2023

#### **MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models**

CONNOR BERNARD, GABRIEL SILVA SANTOS, [...], ERIK KUSCH, [...], ROBERTO SALGUERO-GÓMEZ

Mature Scientific Data - 2023

#### A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

ERICK LUNDGREN, DANIEL RAMP, OWEN MIDDLETON, EAMONN WOOSTER, ERIK KUSCH, [...], ARIAN WALLACH

#### Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

**ᡂ** Journal of Ecology - 2022

#### KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH. RICHARD DAVY

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2022

#### Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2021

## **Honours & Grants & Awards**

#### **SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS**

10/2020	<b>Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students</b> , Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
03/2019	Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
02/2019	Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
03/2018	<b>Project Grant</b> , L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
2018/19	<b>Scholarship</b> , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)	Bonn, Germany

#### **AWARDS**

10/2019	<b>Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher</b> , International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria
10/2019	Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria